Finding Aid for the Jean Renoir Papers PASC.0105
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Part I - Production Files
  - Series XI: PHOTOGRAPHS-PERSONAL/FAMILY
    - RENOIR, JEAN (1970s)
      - - Color photographs of J.R., with and without Dido, during 1970s, (13) items total. - (4) mounted portraits of J.R., one with Dido, dated September 1974. - (6) color photogr. 81st Birthday. - (3) color photogr. J.R. w/ Sophie Renoir (granddaughter). (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - RENOIR, ALAIN
      - - Photographs of Alain Renoir and family, c. 1922-1986, b/w and color, (79) items, with accompanying correspondence. (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - - Photograph album (Dec. 1950/Jan. 1951 to Oct. 1953) covering early years of John and Peter Renoir. Oversized book. (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - RENOIR, JEAN and DIDO FREIRE
      - - Portraits, b/w, by Man Ray, 1949, (3) of Jean and (9) of Dido Freire Renoir. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - - Oversize photograph, in front of Hollywood drugstore exterior, b/w, [see box 21, folder 1 for same photo, 8"x10"] (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - - Oversize photographs of Jean and Dido Renoir, New York, 1958, b/w, (2) items. (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - - Photographs of Dido with Jean Renoir, as "Mrs. Jean Renoir" on public and private occasions, c. 1940's-1970's, (57) items total. (49) b/w items, (8) color (1 mounted). (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - FREIRE (RENOIR), DIDO
      - - Oversize portrait, b/w, 1983 (79 years old). - Oversize collage of 3 children (FotoPreuss, Rio de Janiero), b/w. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - - Photographs of Dido Renoir, from 1940's-1987, (19) b/w, (11) color. (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - - Photographs, b/w, in album, of Dido Freire Renoir's family and friends, c. 1920's. - Personal items belonging to Dido Freire Renoir, 3 items total. (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - - (Loose) photographs, (85) b/w and (186) color, of Dido Renoir's family and friends, 1910-1987. - Miscellaneous negatives from photos. (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - - Photographs of Dido Freire Renoir and relatives, some mounted/slipcased, (9) b/w, (3) color. (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - RENOIR, JEAN (HOMES)
      - - Photographs of the Renoir homes on Martel and Leona Drives in Los Angeles, c. 1940-1985, (27) items total. Martel Drive, b/w, (2) items. Leona Drive, color, (25) items. (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - - Stereoscopic slide viewer and glass slides of the Renoir home on Leona Drive, December 1951, January 1952, 1959, and 1960. (Box 24, Folder unknown container)
    - RENOIR, JEAN (with unidentified people)
      - - Photographs taken of acquaintances and friends on various occasions, with and without Jean and Dido Freire Renoir, (25) items, incl. 1 by Man Ray), b/w and color. - Slides of same, (7) items, accompanying letter. (Box 17, Folder 66)
      - - Miscellaneous photographs of Renoir with various (unidentified) individuals, b/w, (16) items. (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - - Photographs and snapshots, with and without J. R. and Dido with pets: Dogs, (46) b/w items, (1) cutout, (3) color. - Cats, (44) b/w items, (1) color photo, (5) slides. Total of (105) items plus negatives. (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - RENOIR, PIERRE-AUGUSTE
      - - Portrait with Aline and Claude "Coco" Renoir. Oversized. (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - - Photographs of Pierre-Auguste Renoir, Aline Renoir, Pierre Renoir, Claude Renoir, Sr., Claude Renoir, Jr., and Vera Sergine Renoir, 1900-1917, (49) items. (Box 20, Folder 3)
      - - Glass plate negatives of photographs of the Renoir family, c. 1910-1919. (Box 27, Folder unknown container)
  - Series XII: PERSONAL ITEMS
    - unspecified
      - - Personal items belonging to Dido Renoir. (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - - Drawing of the Renoir kitchen at Leona Drive, 11/30/52. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - - Notebook with household expenses for 1615 N. Martel, Los Angeles. 1942-43. (Box 52, Folder 1)
      - - J.R.'s pension books from the French army, 1936-1938: 2 booklets, 4 pages, 1 envelope. (Box 52, Folder 2)
      - - J.R.'s military papers relating to pension and discharge, spanning 1930's. (Box 52, Folder 3)
      - - "Livret de famille" for J.R.'s marriage to Andree Heuschling, 1/17/20. (Box 52, Folder 4)
      - - Receipts for C.A.R.E. packages sent to friends and family after World War II., 1946-1948. (Box 52, Folder 5)
      - - Inventories of J.R.'s furniture and artwork, including lists of those to be sent from France after World War II. (Box 52, Folder 6)
      - - Personal inventories/compilations of J.R.'s films, interviews, books, unpublished texts, and projects, dated 1979-1980. (Box 52, Folder 7)
      - - Lease agreement for J.R's home at 8150 Hollywood Blvd, 1/22/41. (Box 52, Folder 9)
      - - Legal documents concerning the founding of the Cinematheque Francaise by Henri Langlois and Pierre Harle, 4 copies, 9/2/36. (Box 52, Folder 22)
      - - Postcards from World War I, (7) items total. - Pamphlet, "Historique Campagne Contre L'Allemagne de 1914 a 1919." (Box 53, Folder 3)
      - - Two notebooks with handwritten notes and 2 handwritten pages dating from the time of J.R.'s service in the French Cinematographic Corps during World War II. (Box 53, Folder 4)
      - - Ration books, coupons and stamps for J.R. and Dido Freire Renoir during World War II (1942-43). - Voting stubs, 1 postcard, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 5)
      - - Lists of names and addresses of friends, 2 pages, n.d. - List of tape recordings owned by J.R., 1 page, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 6)
      - - Italian driving permits for J.R. and Dido Renoir, 9/15/52. (Box 53, Folder 7)
      - - Pedigree books, certificates, etc., concerning the Renoirs' dogs, 1940's-1970's. (Box 53, Folder 8)
      - - Autographed menu from a dinner celebrating "La Bete Humaine," 1 page, 3/12/39. - "La Restaurant bar de Centre Jean Renoir," souvenir menu, n.d. - Handmade birthday "card" from MOMA Film Dept. staff, 9/15/74. (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - BIOGRAPHICAL DATA
      - - Biographical questionnaire for Twentieth Century Fox, w/ J.R's vital statistics/information, 1/25/41, subseq. revised/updated (?date). - Bio/fact sheet, 2 pgs, 3/27/58. - "Notes on Jean Renoir," 2 pgs, n.d. - Aesthetic ethos (?author), 2 pgs, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - HONORS/TRIBUTES/RETROSPECTIVES
      - - Scrapbook: "Semaine Jean Renoir," Cine-Club de la Jeunesse showing of "Le Carosse d'Or," "Le Dejeuner Sur L'Herbe," and "Une Partie de Campagne," December, 1959, incl. clippings, invitations, schedules. (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - - Programs from diverse retrospective film series, 1962-1977, commemorating J.R.'s film oeuvre. (Box 30, Folder 17)
      - - Program from a "Special Tribute to J.R." at the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, 11/19/76. (Box 52, Folder 10)
      - - Transcription of Royal College of Art (London) convocation programme, incl. awarding of honorary Ph.D. in absentia to J.R., 7/9/71. (Box 53, Folder 9)
      - - UCLA Charter Day Program, incl. awarding of honorary degree to J.R., 4/4/63. - Program for UCLA Winter 1964 Film Series, "The American Film and Its Creators," incl. J.R. w/ "The Little Matchseller" and "Southerner," 2/16/64. (Box 53, Folder 10)
      - - "Grande Semaine de l'Universite, du 19 au 28 fevrier [?year], calendrier des manifestations a la Sorbonne": notice of "Hommage a J.R," plus extract fr/ special "J.R." issue of Cahiers du Cinema, Noel 1957, re J.R. re "Grande Illusion," unpaginated. (Box 53, Folder 11)
      - - Program for 1959-60 Golden and Silver Laurel Awards Presentation (with J.R.'s name listed as prior recipient on back), 2/14/60. (Box 53, Folder 21)
      - - Notice of symposium w/ J.R. scheduled as participant/featured speaker, "The Role of Films in International Cultural Relations," date unknown. - Oct. 1963 issue of "Author & Journalist" w/ J.R. photo and quote on cover. (Box 53, Folder 22)
      - - Announcements, obituaries and tributes occasioned by J.R.'s death. (Box 54, Folder 5)
      - - Programs from film retrospective, 1961-1975, devoted exclusively or in part to J.R. and his film oeuvre. (Box 55, Folder 13)
    - LETTRES D'AMERIQUE
      - - Articles from newspapers and magazine re: "Lettres D'Amerique." (Box 30, Folder 9)
      - - Introduction and notes for "Lettres d'Amerique," by Dido Renoir, 8 pages, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 17)
    - NICHOLS, DUDLEY
      - - Poem about the film, "The River," by Dudley Nichols, translated into French by Jean Renoir. (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - RENOIR CINEMA, NYC
      - - Articles regarding the formation of the "Renoir Cinema" in New York, c. 1977. (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - RENOIR, CLAUDE
      - - Typed script of narration (to be read by J.R.) for film on Cezanne by Claude Renoir, Jr., "Commentaire pour Cezanne, Court Metrage de Claude Renoir," 17 pages (plus fragment of 18th page), includes accompanying letter, 12/2/59. (Box 53, Folder 13)
      - - Text of a speech by Alain Renoir, June 1973. - Extract from an article by Alain Renoir, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 16)
    - RENOIR, PIERRE-AUGUSTE
      - - Photographs, b/w, 5 items,and 2 programs, documenting/detailing creation of Musee Renoir, Chateau de Cagnes, 11/4/50. (Box 20, Folder 6)
      - - Exhibition brochure from 1972 Los Angeles gallery exhibit. - Christian Science Monitor review (counterpointing exhibit with Pierre-Auguste Renoir's "Jean Renoir with Cookie"), 12/18/72, (2) items. (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - - Photographs from the Art Institute of Chicago's exhibition of Pierre-Auguste Renoir's paintings, (18) items, color, February 1973. (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - - Photographic reproductions of paintings by Pierre-Auguste Renoir, incl. portraits of J.R. and/or Gabrielle Renard Slade, b/w, (44) items total. - Postcard and notecard reproductions, (7) color, (1) b/w. (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - - Photographic reproductions of notes by Pierre-Auguste Renoir, b/w, (2) items. (Box 20, Folder 14)
      - - Photocopies of letters from Eduoard Manet and Claude Monet to Pierre-Auguste Renoir, 14 pages total, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 15)
      - - Reprint from Gazette des Beaux-Arts, "Auguste Renoir and His Brother," by John Rewald, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 16)
      - - Oversize photographs (4), color. - (1) experimental photograph by Walter Allen. - (4) color reproductions of Renoir paintings. (Box 25, Folder 6)
      - - Pamphlet/articles: "The Mastery Of Arthritis By A Master of Painting, Pierre-Auguste Renoir," n.d. - Renoir exhibit, Boston, 1985. - "La Vie Artistique," by Henry Asselin, 4 pages, 1962. -"Renoir und Gabrielle," by Willi Schub, 1960. (Box 52, Folder 23)
      - - Certificate of authenticity regarding one of P.-A.'s paintings, 1939. - Color transparency of same, 1 item, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 27)
    - SERGE, JEAN
      - - "Project de Film sur Jean Renoir," by Jean Serge, 2 pages, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 28)
  - Series XIII: MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS
    - unspecified
      - - Photographs, b/w, (7) items, taken by Joao de Freitas Martino, 1940. (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - - Photographs, b/w, (7) items, incl. (1) oversized, from Flaherty's film, "Elephant Boy," 1935. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - - Photographs and sketches of miscellaneous artworks. (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - - Photographs, b/w, of artworks by Jacqueline Andre-Bret, incl. a painting of J.R., (3) items, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - - Photographic reproductions primarily of 19th-c. portraits/landscapes, b/w, (57) items. (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - - Costume design watercolor sketch by Bernard Larotte for "Flight to Arras," n.d. (Box 25, Folder 7)
      - - Sheet music c. 1930, "Ninon, Je Vous Aime" and "Celle des Fauches". (Box 25, Folder 8)
      - - Copy of "Screenwriter's Guild Magazine", July 1945. - Information regarding the French Army in the U.S., n.d. (Box 52, Folder 8)
      - - Personalized invitation/announcement of MOMA exhibit by Fernand Leger, 1940-41. (Box 52, Folder 29)
      - - Unidentified, handwritten notes. - Sheet music for "En Revenant de la Revue," n.d. (Box 53, Folder 23)
      - - Script of "Linkletter's House Party" T.V. show, 11/15/62. (Box 54, Folder 8)
      - - "A Walk in Alabama": public address given on April 6, 1965 to the School of Library Service, UCLA, by Guy Endore, 17 pages. (Box 54, Folder 18)
      - - Program from an exhibition of the works of Berthe Morisot, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 19)
      - - Program from an exhibition of works by Marcel Gimond, July-September 1965. (Box 54, Folder 20)
- Part II - Correspondence
  - 1913-1915
    - Letters from J.R. to his family while in the hospital during World War I. - letter to J.R.'s commanding officer requesting a transfer to an aviation squadron. Photocopies only. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Andre, Albert * Renoir, Aline * Renoir, Pierre-Auguste * Renoir, Claude, Sr. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - MARCH-APRIL 1923
    - Donation of Pierre-Auguste Renoir painting to France - includes photocopied letters to and from Jean and Pierre Renoir. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Pierre (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - JANUARY-FEBRUARY 1925
    - Release of and reaction to LA FILLE DE L'EAU in the United States, Harold Van Doren to Jean and Claude Renor. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Van Doren, Harold * FILLE DE L'EAU, LA (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1934
    - J.R.'s attempt to make TONI - formation of "Les Films d'Aujourd'hui" - J.R.'s resignation from "Syndicat des Chef Cineastes Francais". Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Koch, Carl * Renoir, Alain * TONI * FILMS D'AUJOURD'HUI, LES (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1936
    - J.R. engaged to direct LES BAS FONDS - J.R. nominated to be awarded Chevalier De La Legion D'Honneur. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * BAS FONDS, LES * Spaak, Charles (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1937
    - J.R. awarded Chevalier de la Legion d'honneur - Yugoslavian ban of LA GRANDE ILLUSION and plagarism alleged by Jean des Vallieres (author of "Kavalier-Scharnhorst") and Albin Michel (publisher) - project of contractual correspondence with R.A.C. (Realizations d'Art Cinematographiques) - reactions to LA GRANDE ILLUSION - pre-production issues re LA MARSELLAISE. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Des Vallieres, Jean * Michel, Albin * Aragon, Louis * Spaak, Charles * Pinsard, Col. * MARSEILLAISE, LA (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1938
    - Offer by Samuel Goldwyn to work in U.S.A. - J.R. requests to work for the French Cinematography Corps in case of war - research for and shooting of LA BETE HUMAINE - J.R.'s speech at the Sorbonne on Emile Zola - confirmation contract for LA BETE HUMAINE - projects "Trip to Tilsit" and "La Journal d'une Femme de Chambre" (Diary of a Chambermaid) - telegrams re: LA MARSEILLAISE. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Goldwyn, Samuel * Renoir, Alain * Slade, Gabrielle * LeBlond-Zola, Maurice * Hirschmann, Andre * Pinkewich, Albert * MARSEILLAISE, LA * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * TRIP TO TILSIT (project) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1939
    - J.R. and Dido Freire working on LA TOSCA in Italy - beginning of World War II - military correspondence - letters from Dido Freire's family in England - release of LA REGLE DU JEU - telegram announcing LA GRANDE ILLUSION's winning of the N.Y. Film Critics Award for the Best Foreign Film of 1938. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert * Guillaume, Louis * Renoir, Alain * Ivens, Joris * REGLE DU JEU, LA * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * TOSCA, LA (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - APRIL 1940
    - Letters from Dido Freire's family and friends - Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Guillaume, Louis (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - MAY 1940
    - Letters to and from J.R. and Dido Freire during work on LA TOSCA in Italy - J.R. considers leaving for U.S.A. - Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - JULY 1940
    - Wartime events in France - telegrams re: J.R. and Dido Freire attempts to arrange passage to U.S.A. - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert * Rochemont, Richard de * Tual, Denise (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AUGUST 1940
    - Letters to and from J.R. and Dido Freire - attempts to leave France - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert * Rochemont, Richard de * Vignancour, Tixier (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - SEPTEMBER 1940
    - J.R. and Dido Freire attempts to acquire Visa's to leave for U.S.A. - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - OCTOBER 1940
    - J.R. and Dido Freire acquisition of Visa's for trip to Lisbon and departure to U.S.A. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Cezanne, Paul, Jr. * Flaherty, Robert * Rochemont, Richard de * Daven, Andre (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - NOVEMBER 1940
    - Letters to and from J.R. and Dido Freire - trip to Lisbon for departure to U.S.A. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Hakim, Robert (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - DECEMBER 1940
    - J.R. and Dido Freire depart for U.S.A., arrival in New York - welcoming telegrams from friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Clair, Rene * Flaherty, Robert * Rochemont, Richard de * Daven, Andre * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Vignancour, Tixier (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - JANUARY 1941
    - J.R. and Dido Freire arrive in New York - greetings - immigration problems for family and friends - U.S. film industry - wartime monetary restrictions - renting house on Hollywood Blvd. - project: "Venezuela" - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Henry-Haye, Gaston * Renoir, Alain * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Vignancour, Tixier * Lourie, Eugene * Lestringuez, Pierre * Feldman, Charles * Flaherty, Robert * Von Stroheim, Erich * Daven, Andre * Zanuck, Darryl F. * VENEZUELA (project) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - FEBRUARY 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - J.R. signs with Twentieth Century Fox Studios - beginning of SWAMP WATER - going to Georgia for location scouting - news of friends - invitations - requests for immigration help for friends in France. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Alain * Flaherty, Robert * Flaherty, David * Lubitsch, Ernst * Ivens, Joris * Lazareff, Pierre * SWAMP WATER (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - MARCH 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - life in Occupied France - letter from Vereen Bell to Dudley Nichols re: SWAMP WATER - news of family and friends - memos from Darryl F. Zanuck re: SWAMP WATER - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Gabrielle * Braunberger, Pierre * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Bell, Vereen * SWAMP WATER * Daven, Andre * Renoir, Alain * Lubitsch, Ernst * Zanuck, Darryl F. * Nichols, Dudley * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - APRIL 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - state of French film industry during the German occupation - memos from Darryl F. Zanuck re: projects "Venezuela", "I Wake Up Screaming" and "Wind, Sand, and Stars"- requests for help from friends and family in France. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Alain * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Nichols, Dudley * SWAMP WATER * Feldman, Charles * Blum, Ralph * Clair, Rene * Florian, Werner * David, Charles (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - MAY 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - memos from Darryl Zanuck re: projects "I Wake Up Screaming" and "Wind, Sand, and Stars"; SWAMP WATER: casting, location shooting in Florida and Georgia - invitations - life and film industry in Occupied France - J.R. invited to join the Screen Director's Guild - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Robert * Zanuck, Darryl F. * SWAMP WATER * Leger, Fernand * Ivens, Joris * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Feldman, Charles * Cezanne, Paul, Jr. * Cezanne, Renee * Barnes, Albert * Rainer, Luise * Milhaud, Darius * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Alain * Hirschmann, Andre * Lourie, Eugene * Andre, Albert (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - JUNE 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - film industry in Occupied France - news of family and friends - memos from Darryl F. Zanuck re: casting and production of SWAMP WATER - location shooting in Georgia - J.R. trying to interest studios in "Wind, Sand, and Stars" - J.R. inducted into the Screen Director's Guild - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Zanuck, Darryl F. * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * SWAMP WATER * Nichols, Dudley * Lang, Fritz * Pichel, Irving * Clair, Rene * Renoir, Alain * Lestringuez, Pierre * Chomette, Henri * Slade, Gabrielle * Andre, Albert * Temps, Paul (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - JULY 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - J.R. trying to interest producers in "Wind, Sand, and Stars" - working on SWAMP WATER - memos from Darryl F. Zanuck - state of French film industry - potential projects with Dudley Nichols - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Alain * Zanuck, Darryl F. * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Vaughan, Olwen * Bell, Vereen * Nichols, Dudley * Pichel, Irving * Boyer, Charles * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Florian, Werner * Kosma, Joseph * SWAMP WATER (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AUGUST 1941
    - News of family and friends in France - memos from Darryl F. Zanuck re: rushes of SWAMP WATER - death of Henri Chomette - J.R.'s problems with SWAMP WATER. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Esta * Renoir, Pierre * Zanuck, Darryl F. * SWAMP WATER * Nichols, Dudley * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Lourie, Eugene * Slade, Gabrielle * Boyer, Charles * Chomette, Henri * Milhaud, Darius (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - SEPTEMBER 1941
    - J.R.'s problems with SWAMP WATER - project "Hunky" with Dudley Nichols - attempts to get Joseph Kosma in U.S.A.- Alain Renoir's immigration problems. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Leger, Fernand * Nichols, Dudley * Renoir, Alain * Vaughan, Olwen * Moguy, Leonide * Lourie, Eugene * Slade, Gabrielle * Kracauer, Siegfried * Renoir, Paulette * SWAMP WATER * Kosma, Joseph (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - OCTOBER 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration problems - arrival of the Slades to Los Angeles - projects with Dudley Nichols. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Alain * Lorentz, Pare * Wanger, Walter * Slade, Gabrielle (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - NOVEMBER 1941
    - Alain Renoir's immigration to U.S.A. - project "Jarka" - invitations - publicity for SWAMP WATER in Waycross, Georgia - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Alain * Rainer, Luise * Lourie, Eugene * Lazareff, Pierre * Kosma, Joseph * SWAMP WATER (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - DECEMBER 1941
    - Arrival of Alain Renoir to U.S.A. - news from family and friends in France - reactions to SWAMP WATER. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Lazareff, Pierre * Lourie, Eugene * Renoir, Alain * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Paulette * Lamotte, Bernard * SWAMP WATER * Wanger, Walter * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Stevens, George (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - JANUARY 1942
    - French Ambassador's request for J.R. to return to France - film projects - Claude Renoir, Sr.'s attempted immigration to U.S.A. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Paulette * Renoir, Alain * Saint-Exupery, Antoine de * Huston, Walter * Lamotte, Bernard (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - FEBRUARY 1942
    - War correspondence from Alain Renoir - project with Deanna Durbin at Universal - charity appeals - project of book on Pierre-Auguste Renoir - purchase of home on Martel Ave. - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Pagnol, Marcel * Renoir, Alain * Lourie, Eugene * Flaherty, Robert * Koster, Henry * Henry-Haye, Gaston * Evans, Ernestine * Nichols, Dudley (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - MARCH 1942